本周我们看了两个公钥加密系统类型
This week, we saw two families of public
encryption systems. One family was built
一个是基于陷门函数的，特别是RSA
from trapdoor functions, and particularly
RSA, and the other family was built from
另一类是基于Diffie-Hellman协议构建的。在这最后一节里
the Diffie-Hellman protocol. In this last
segment, I wanna show you that both
我想给大家展示实际上这两类机制遵循着一个更一般的原理
families in fact follow from a more
general principle. The unifying theme is
这个统一的主题叫做单向函数。那么什么是单向函数？
what's called a one-way function. So what
is a one-way function? Well, we've already
我们之前已经简要地看过这一概念。它是一个函数
seen this concept briefly before. But
basically, a function from, one set to
从一个集合映射到另一个集合，比如说从X到Y，
这个函数是单向的，如果事实上有一个有效的算法
another, say, from X to Y is said to be
one way, if, in fact, there's an efficient
允许我们计算函数F。那么任何人都可以计算函数F
algorithm that allows us to evaluate the
function F. So anyone can evaluate the
在他们选择的任一点的值。但是，求函数F的逆
function F at any point of their choice.
However, inverting the function F should
应当是困难的。这就让这个函数是单向的了
be difficult. That's what makes the
function one way. So what do I mean by
我的话是什么意思？大家可以把函数F想象成
that? Well, you can think of the function
F as a function again mapping the set X to
从集合X到集合Y的映射，但许多X中的点实际上
the set Y. But it so happens in many
points in X could actually be mapped into
可以被映射到Y中的单个点。现在当他们说，
这个函数求逆是困难的
a single point in Y. Now when they say
that the function is difficult to invert,
意思是，当我给你某个Y中的点，我让你去找
what I mean is that when I give you some
point inside of Y and I ask you find me
这个点的原像，你将无法指出这个点的任何一个原像
pre-image of this point, you won't be able
to point to any of these as a pre-image.
换句话说，没有有效算法可以找到任何给定Y中的点的
In other words, no efficient algorithm can
find any point that is the inverse of the
原像。现在我们说的更准确点，对于所有
given point Y. Now the way we say that
more precisely is that we say that for all
有效算法A，如果我选择一个集合X中的随机元素x
efficient algorithm A, if I chose a random
X in the set, capital X, and now I'm gonna
现在我把f(x)给算法A，然后我让算法A
give f(x) to algorithm A. And then, what
I'm gonna ask algorithm A to do, is
去产生一个点f(x)的原像。A产生点f(x)的一个原像
basically produce a pre-image of the point
f(x). Well, what does it mean that A
是什么意思？它的意思是，如果我应用函数f
produced a pre-image of the point f(x)? It
means that if I apply the function f to
对A的输出进行作用，我应该可以重新获得f(x)
the output of A, what I should get back
is, well, f(x). Let's think through this
我们再讲一般。那么我选择一个X中的随机点x
one more time. So I chose a random point x
in Capital X. You know I give algorithm A
我给算法A以f(x)。那么我把这个点给算法A。现在
f(x). So I'm gonna give algorithm A this
point here. And now A is gonna produce
A将产生某些点。那么我们假定A产生这里的这个点
some points. So let's pretend that A
produces this point over here. And now I
现在我想说如果我对这个点应用函数F，那么A
wanna say that if I apply the function F
to this point here, that A produced, the
给我输出的点与最初的x一样的概率是可忽略的
probability that I get the same point that
I started with is negligible. In other
换句话说，算法能产生这三个点中的一个的概率
words the probability that algorithm A
was able to produce one of these three points is, in
实际上是可忽略的。他只能产生某个其他的点
fact, negligible. All he can do is produce
some other point that maps into something
其映射结果不是f(x)，对吧？所有这些都是在试图抓住
other than f(x), okay? So, again, all
this is trying to do is just capture the
给定f(x)，很难找到f(x)的原像这一事实
fact that given f(x), it's hard to find
some pre-image of f(x). So here's some
这里有一些这样的函数的简单例子，它们不是单向的
easy examples of functions that are not
one-way. For example, the identity
比如恒等函数f(x)=x是简单的，不是单向的，因为
function f(x) is equal to x is trivially
not one way because given f(x), I can
有了f(x)，我可以轻易地指出f(x)的逆，即x
easily come up with an inverse of f(x),
namely x. Similarly the function that will
类似地，把一切都映射到0的函数也不是单向的。
在我们的图里，设有一函数
maps everything to zero is also not one
way. So in our picture, let the function
将一切都映射成0，看起来如下。它把所有点
maps everything to zero simply looks as
follows. It takes all its points and maps
都映射到单个点。这个函数不是单向的
them all to a single point. Well this
function is not one way because if I give
因为我给你了像里的这个点，容易找出一个原像
you this point in the image, it's trivial
to find the pre-image. Namely, just pick
(严格地说，这里应该是 a pre-image)
只要选取X中的任一点，都会是0的原像
any point in capital X, and there will be
a pre-image of zero. And so, f(x) equal
那么f(x)=0并非单向函数。顺便一说，这里我不想严格地
to zero is also not a one-way function.
And by the way, I didn't want to do it
定义单向函数，但如果我要形式化地给出定义
here. But if I define one-way functions
more formally, then it turns out that
那么实际上要证明单向函数是否存在，
我们就必须证明P不等于NP
proving that one-way functions exist,
we'll have also proven that P is not equal
因为我们目前不能证明P不等于NP
to NP. So, since we can't today, prove
that P is not equal to NP, basically we
(若P=NP，则公钥密码学将有根基危机)
我们也不能证明单向函数的存在性。我们只是假设它们存在。
can't prove that one-way functions exist.
And we just have to assume that they do.
那么我们看我们的第一个单向函数的例子
So let's look at our first example of a
1-way function. Or at least a presumed
或至少假设为单向函数。那么我们使用一个
伪随机数发生器来构造它
1-way function. And so we're gonna build
it from a pseudo random generator. And
假设我有一个函数F，从X映射到Y，
则有一个安全的伪随机数发生器
suppose I have a function F from x to y
there is a secure pseudo random generator.
F的输出比输入长得多。还记得
So the output of F is much larger than
the input. Remember, a pseudo-random
一个伪随机数发生器取一个小种子，
把它扩成了更长的输出
generator takes a small seed and expands
it into a much larger output. And for
例如大家可以使用确定的计数器模式与AES
example you can, you know, the pseudo
random generator maybe is built using
来构建伪随机数发生器。容易看出
deterministic counter mode out of AES.
Well, it's fairly easy to see that if, in
如果事实上F是安全的伪随机数发生器，那么F事实上
fact, F is a secure pseudo random
generator, then F is in fact a one-way
是一个单向函数。我们的第一个例子是直接由
function. So our first example of a
one-way function is directly built from a
伪随机数发生器构造的。这是一个简单的证明
pseudo random generator. This is actually
kind of a trivial proof, so let's prove
我们来证明它的逆否命题。
假设我有一个有效算法可以求F的逆
the contra positive. So suppose I have an
efficient algorithm that inverts F, okay?
那么我要证明其逆否命题。假设F不是单向的
So I'm proving the contra positive.
Suppose F is not one way. Then A is an
那么A是一个求F的逆的有效算法。
现在我需要构建一个算法B
efficient algorithm than an inverse F. And
now I need to build an algorithm B that
来破解这个伪随机数发生器。好，那么我还是证逆否
breaks the pseudorandom generator. Ok, so I'm proving again by contra-positive. Okay so how do I break the
我该如何破解这个伪随机数发生器呢？我们只要这么做
pseudo-random generator? Well, all we do
is the following. So algorithm B is given
算法B有集合Y中的某个元素y，它做如下事情
some y in the set Y. And what it's gonna
do is the following, it's gonna try and
算法B试着对输入y运行算法A。现在，如果y是
run algorithm A on the input y. And now,
well, if y is the output of the
伪随机数发生器的输出，那么算法A就会输出种子
pseudorandom generator, then algorithm A
will output the seed, and namely
即X中的一个元素，以不可忽略的概率
an element in X with, you know,
non-negligible probability. So what
我们再次对算法A的输出应用这个伪随机数发生器
we'll do is we'll apply the pseudorandom
generator again to the output of algorithm
如我所说，如果y是发生器的输出，然后A会输出种子
A. As I said, if y was the output of a
generator, then A will have output
因为它能求伪随机数发生器的逆。那么如果我们
the seed cuz it inverted the pseudorandom
generator. So if we apply the pseudorandom
对A的输出应用再次伪随机数发生器，
我们应该重新得到开始时的y
generator again to the output of A, what
we should get back is basically the y that
好，那么如果这个条件成立的话，我们说
we started with. Okay, so if this
condition holds we're gonna say we're
我们输出0，如果这个条件不成立，我们输出1
gonna output zero. And if this condition
doesn't hold, we're gonna output one
完事了，这就是我们区分出伪随机数发生器的方法
otherwise. That's it, that's our
distinguisher against a pseudo-random
那么如果我们的方法是，给定伪随机数发生器的输出y
generator. So if our distinguisher is
given a y that is the output of the pseudo
那么以不可忽略的概率，我们的算法B
random generator, then with non-negligible
probability, our distinguisher B will
输出0。但是如果给算法B一个真随机字符串
output zero. However, if our distinguisher
B is given a truly random string. Well, a
一个真随机字符串不由发生器的任何种子生成
truly random string doesn't have any seed
that causes the generator to output that
所以我们的区分算法就会输出1，以非常高的概率
string. And therefore our distinguishable
output one with again, with also very high
我希望这里说清楚了。如果我们看所有可能的输出集合
probability. And again I hope that's
clear. Basically, if we look at the set of
即集合Y中很少有元素
all possible outputs, namely the set Y,
very few of those outputs happened to
是伪随机数发生器的输出
be the output of the pseudorandom
generator. So if we are just given an
如果我们有个y，据说不是伪随机数发生器的输出
output y over hearsay, that's not the
output of the pseudorandom generator, then
那么我们重新运行算法A。它不可能产生一个种子
we rerun algorithm A on it. It can't
possibly produce a seed that will output
会输出这个带*的点，因为不存在这样的种子。因此
this point star because there is no
such seed. And as a result, since most
由于大多数的点不在伪随机数发生器的像里
points actually are not in the image of
the pseudorandom generator, most points
大部分的点没有种子，让发生器映射到它们
will not have a seed that, maps the
generator to them and there's also where
我们有Y中的一个随机点，一个真均匀分布的随机点
we were given a random point in Y, a truly
uniform point in Y, our distinguishable B
我们的区分算法B会以很高的概率输出1。
但是如果我们有
will output 1 with very high
probability. However, if we are given a
一个伪随机数发生器的输出，那么算法A会输出
pseudo random output of a generator, then
algorithm A will output the corresponding
对应的种子。当我们对这个种子应用发生器，
我们会获得最初的输出y
seed. When we apply the generator to that
seed, we'll get the initial output y and
因此我们会以不可忽略的概率输出0
therefore we'll output zero with
non-negligible probability. Okay, so if A
那么如果A可以求F的逆，那么B也可以破解发生器
was able to invert F, then B is able to
break the generator. And since the
因为这个发生器是安全的，所以A不可能求F的逆
generator is secure, algorithm A can't
invert F. And in particular, no efficient
特别地，没有有效算法可以求F的逆，因此F是一个单向函数
algorithm can invert F. And therefore, F
is a one-way function. Excellent, so this
这一小点讨论了很长。我想给大家证实
is a long discussion of kind of a minor
point. But all I wanted to show you is
事实上伪随机数发生器直接给了我们一个单向函数
that in fact, a pseudo-random generator
directly gives us a one-way function.
不幸的是，这个单向函数没有特别的性质
Unfortunately, this one-way function has
no special properties. And what that means
意思是说，实际上很难使用他，以进行密钥交换或公钥加密
is it's actually difficult to use it for
key exchange or for public key encryption.
某种意义上，我们能做的最好的密钥交换
In some sense, the best key exchange we
can do with this, as far as we know, is
目前我们知道的是Merkle谜题。那么现在我们看第二个例子
Merkle puzzles. So now let's look at
our second example. The second example is
第二个例子是，我们称离散对数是单向函数。
那么我们固定选取一个群
what I'm gonna call the discrete log one
way function. So let's fix a group, a
一个N阶循环群G，设g为G中一个生成元
cyclic group of order N the group G and
let g be some generator of the group
我再提醒大家一下，这意味着，如果我看
capital G so again I remind you that all
that means is, if I look at all powers of
g的各次幂，我可以得到整个群G的各个元素。现在我们定义
g, then I basically span the entire group
capital G. And now let's define the
如下函数。这个函数从Z_N映射到G，并定义为
following function. The function goes from
ZN to G and it's defined basically as the
x的幂的指数。好的，那么这个函数把任一从0到n-1的
exponentiation to the power of X. Okay, so
this maps any element between zero and n-1
整数映射到群G中的一个元素，通过计算g的幂
to an element of the group capital G
simply by raising g, little g to the
g的适当次幂。显然，如果群G上的离散对数问题
appropriate power. And it's kind of
obvious that if the discrete log problem
是困难的，那么事实上函数f是单向的
in the group capital G is hard, then in
fact f is one way. In fact, the one
f的单向性就是离散对数假设。如果离散对数
wayness of f is the discrete log
assumption. So if the discrete log is
是难于计算的，f就是单向的。现在有趣的是
hard, f is one way. Now the interesting
thing about this one-way functions is it's
这个单向函数有一些有趣的性质。特别是，如果我你
got some interesting properties. In
particular, if I give you f(x) and f(y)
f(x)和f(y)，我宣布，容易计算f(x+y)，即使我们不知道
I claim that it's very easy to compute
f(x + y). Even though we have no idea
x和y是什么。我们只有f(x)和f(y)
what x or y are. All we're given is just f(x) and f(y), nevertheless, we can
不过我们可以计算f(x+y)。我问大家，该怎么做？
compute f(x + y). Let me ask you, how
would you do that? Well, just by rules of
就用指数规则，f(x+y)=f(x)f(y)
exponentiation, basically, f(x + y)
is simply f(x) times f(y). And again,
这些都是在群G上完成的。如果你不相信，回忆一下
this is all done inside the group G. If
you're not convinced, simply recall that f(x + y)
f(x+y)=g^(x+y)=(g^x)(g^y)
is g to the (x + y). Which is
simply g to the x times g to the y, which
(注意到这是一个群同态，ElGamal属于部分同态加密)
即为我们这里的值。这个简单性质
is exactly what we have here. And this
simple property, this simple fact that the
函数有这个加性性质，如果大家想一想
function has this additive property, if
you think about it, is exactly what
它就能够用来实现密钥交换和公钥加密了
enables key exchange and public key
encryption. So, this additional property
那么这个单向函数的加性使公钥密码学成为可能
of the one-way function is what enabled
all of public key cryptography. So let's
我们来看下一个例子，RSA单向函数。
你们这里我们选择两个质数
look at our next example the RSA one way
function so here we're going to choose two
p和q，我们把N设为p*q，然后我们选择e
primes p and q we're going to set N to be p
times q then were going to choose e that's
e与φ(N)互质。然后我们定义函数
relatively prime to phi(N). And then, we
define the functions, and simply as a
从Z_N^*到Z_N^*的函数，即f(x)=x^e
function from ZN star to ZN star,
simply as f(x) equals x to the e. Okay,
那么就是计算x的e次方。我们又说，这个函数是单向的
so raising x to the power of e. And again
we say that this function is one way,
就是基于RSA假设的。RSA假设是一个假设
simply under the RSA assumption. Again,
the RSA assumption is the assumption that
要求这个函数是单向的。关于这个函数有趣的是
this function is one way. And the
interesting thing about this function is
它有着和上一张幻灯片类似的性质
that it has properties similar to the one
that we saw on the previous slide, namely
即给定f(x)和f(y)，我们可以计算f(xy)，不是f(x+y)
the given f(x) and f(y), now we can
compute f(xy) as opposed to f(x + y)
那么我们说这个函数有一个乘法性质
So we say that this function has
a multiplicative property as opposed to
而上一张里的非加法性质。但更重要地
the additive property on the previous
slide. But more importantly this is kind of
这还不是这个函数最有趣的地方。真正令人兴奋的是
not the most interesting thing about this
function. The really exciting thing about
事实上这个函数有一个陷门，换句话说
this function is it in fact has a
trapdoor. In other words there's a secret
有一个私钥可以让我们突然间就能计算这个函数的逆了
key that all of a sudden allows us to
invert this function. Even though without
不过没有私钥时这个函数是单向的。目前我们知道
the secret key the function is one way. As
far as we know. And this property, I'll
这个具有陷门的性质，使得公钥密码学成为可能
say, the fact that it has a trap door,
again, enabled all of public key
我说这个陷门也使得RSA函数
cryptography. I'll say that this trap door
also makes the RSA function especially
特别适合于数字签名。在第七周我们将看到
well suited for digital signatures. In
week seven, we're gonna see that both the
(第七周将是第二季的第一周，敬请期待)
RSA函数和离散对数函数都能让我们构建
RSA function and the discrete log
functions let us construct digital
数字签名。但因为RSA函数有陷门
signatures. But the RSA function, because
it has a trap door, makes it very, very
使得用RSA构建数字签名特别容易。那么事实上
easy to construct digital signatures from
it. And so, in fact, most digital
世界上的大多数数字签名都是依赖于RSA函数
signatures out there in the world, in
fact, rely on the RSA function just
因为很容易根据RSA构建数字签名。那么
because it's so simple to build digital
signatures from it. So again, we see that
我们看到这个单向函数具有特别的性质
this one-way function with the special
properties. It has a multiplicative
它有乘法性质和陷门。本质上，使得公钥密码学成为可能
property and a trap door. Essentially
again, enables all of public key crypto. So
那么总结一下，我们可以构建公钥密码学的原因
to summarize, the reason we are able to
build public key cryptography namely, the
我们可以进行密钥交换和公钥加密等等的原因
reason we're able to do key exchange and
public key encryption and so on, is
是因为我们可以构建单向函数，它们具备特殊的性质
because we're able to construct one-way
functions that have very, very special
特别地，它们有的这些性质有时叫做
properties. In particular, they have these
properties that are sometimes called
同态性质，即给定f(x)和f(y)
homomorphic properties, namely they're
given f(x) and f(y). We can construct
我们可以构建f(x+y)或f(xy)，有些函数，比如RSA
a f(x + y) or, f(xy), and
some functions, like RSA, even have trap
即使有陷门，让我们可以非常容易地构建数字签名
doors, which let us build digital
signatures very, very easily. But the main
但是我想给大家展示的要点是，公钥密码学的魔法
thing I wanted to show you is that the
magic of public key crypto is basically made
是由于这些单向函数及其特殊性质才成为可能
possible because of these one-way
functions with their special properties. So
那么本章结束。第七周我们开始讨论数字签名
that's the end of this module and then
in week seven, we'll start with digital signatures.